A Guide to the Poetry Society of Virginia records, 1922-2018
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Poetry Society of Virginia records, 1922-2018
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 53
7 linear feet.
Poetry Society of Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection has been donated to the Special Collections and Archives Department in several sections over the years, beginning in 1967.
Biographical Information
The Poetry Society of Virginia was founded in 1923 at the College of William and Mary by a small group of university faculty members and other Virginia poets. The organization seeks to promote the writing, study, and appreciation of poetry through generating publications, sponsoring a number of writing contests, and holding a variety of events across the state. The Society also plays a role in the selection process of the Virginia Poet Laureate.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of materials created and acquired by members of the Poetry Society of Virginia and document the activities of the organization. Contents date from 1922 to 2018, with the bulk of the collection dating from the 1970s to the 2010s. Materials include annual contest files, student contest files, executive committee records, correspondence, membership lists, newsletters, event files, fliers, bylaws, information about individual poets, poems, and printouts from the organization's website.
Poetry -- Archives. -- Societies, etc.; Poets, American -- Virginia.
- Administrative records, 1937-2018
  - Bylaws, 1975-2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Corporation registration, 2006-2008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Executive committee, 1937, 1950-1952, 1965-2018 (Box 1, Folder 3-13)
  - Financial records, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Grant and fellowship applications, 1989-1991, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letterhead, 1994-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Meeting recording, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Membership directories, 1975-2006 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Membership lists, 1967-1977, 1989-2016 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Membership materials, 1940, 1971-2007, undated (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - National Federation of State Poetry Societies, 1993-2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Officer election materials, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Organizational history, 1937-2011, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Regional meetings, 1964-2016 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Treasurer files, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1922-2013
  - Herndon, Brodie, 1933, 1945-1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mabbot, Thomas, 1953, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - McNally, James, 1973-1993 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Member correspondence, 1968-2000, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Norwood, Robert letters to Mary Evelyn Stiles, 1922-1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Officer correspondence, 1993-2010, undated (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Raymond, Richard, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Society library and collection, 1966-1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Program materials, 1928-2018
  - Academy of American Poets Endowed Prizes, 2001-2010 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Annual contest, 1975-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Annual contest, 1990-2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Annual contest, 2001-2003 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Annual contest, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Annual contest, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Annual contest, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Annual contest, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Annual contest, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Annual contest, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Annual contest, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Annual contest, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Annual contest, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Annual contest, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Annual contest, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Annual contest, 2015 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Annual contest, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - Annual contest, 2017 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Annual contest files, 1955-2018 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - Annual student contest, 1991-2005, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Annual student contest, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Annual student contest, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Annual student contest, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Annual student contest, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Annual student contest, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Annual student contest, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Annual student contest, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Annual student contest, 2017 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Contest chairman materials, 1953-1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Cup contest, 2004-2007 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Diamond Anniversary, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Golden Anniversary, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Highland Festival, 2011-2015 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Irene Leache Memorial contest, 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Musical events, 1971-1973, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Other contests, events, and classes, 1974-2010, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Poet's Corner recording, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Poetry by the Sea, 1976-1989, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Poetry Festival, 1970-2015, undated (Box 5, Folder 20-21)
  - Poetry in the Schools, 2001-2007 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Prize winning poem portfolios, 1956-1960, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Readings and workshops, 1967-2015, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Reunions, 1928, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Slam Richmond, 2003-2007, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Speech, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Association of Teachers of English conference, 2015 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Publicity, 1946-2011
  - Announcements binder, 1954-1964 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Fliers, 1991-2005 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - National Federation of State Poetry Societies newsletter, 1992-2004 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
  - News releases and announcements, 1946-2006, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Newsletter files, 1993-1995, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters, 1973, 1981-2018 (Box 6, 7, Folder 14-18, 1-2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1950-2009, undated (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - Other organizations' newsletters, 1974-2011 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Website, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Website newsletter, 2003-2008 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Poet files, 1926-2016
  - Academy of American Poets, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Attack on America poems from website, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Bickerstaff, Patsy Anne, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Chivers, Thomas Holley, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Garrett, George, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Herndon, Brodie, 1946, 1973-1977, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Lull, Ed, 2012 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Member accomplishments, 1957-2015, undated (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
  - Member anthology, 1991-2003, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Member publications list from website, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Meet Virginia's Poets from website, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Norwood, Robert, 1926-1932, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Obituaries, 1950-2014 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Old Dominion Faculty Emeriti Association, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Photographs, 1994, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Poems, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Poet laureate of Virginia, 1969-2016, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Roses so Red and Lilies so Fair: Songs and Poems of Virginia, 2009 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Round robin poems from website, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Smith, Ron, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Spencer, Anne, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Vlannes, Peppino, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 31)